Guide to the F. Stuart Chapin Publications and Papers, 1945-2015
Chapin, F. Stuart Publications and Papers, 1945-2015
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
F. Stuart Chapin publications and papers, 1945-2015
4092
F. Stuart Chapin, Jr., 1916-
ca. 3.5 cubic ft.
Publications and manuscripts.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Printed and manuscript versions of publications by Chapin.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Francis Stuart Chapin, Jr. was a professor and city and regional planner. Chapin was born in Northampton, Massachusetts and grew up there, in Minneapolis, and in New York. He graduated from the University of Minnesota in 1937 and then attended the Massachusetts Insitute of Technology, where he received a Bachelors degree in Architecture in 1939 and a Masters in City Planning in 1940. He worked as a planner for the Tennessee Valley Authority from 1940-1942 and 1945-1947, serving in the Navy in the South Pacific during the break for World War II. After moving to North Carolina, Chapin worked as Director of City Planning for Greensboro for two years, and he then served on the faculty of the Department of City and Regional Planning at the University of North Carolina in Chapel Hill from 1949 until 1978. After retirement, he moved to White Salmon, Washington, where he served on the Columbia River Gorge Commission from 1987 to 1993. Chapin was a member of the Regional Science Association.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Collection consists primarily of printed and manuscript versions of publications by Chapin. Also includes documentation of his career.
Part of Regional Science Archives.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Chapin, F. Stuart, Jr. (Francis Stuart), 1916-
Subjects:
City planning.; Regional planning.; City planners.; College teachers.; Regional science.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- James Anderson, 1970-71 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- V. Artiomov, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Ian Cullen, 1971-74 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Peter Dickens, 1972-73 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Torsten Hagerstrand, 1962-73 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Andrew S. Harvey, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
- Frank E. Horton and David R. Reynolds (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Murray Melbin, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- William Michelson, 1969-75 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Muriel Nissel, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Don Parkes, 1974-75 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- V. D. Patrieshev, 1966-70 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- John P. Robinson, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Gehard Schurer, 1977-78 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Nigel J. Thrift, 1974-75 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Henry Zentner (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Time Studies, 1939-66 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Time Studies, 1957-70 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Time Studies, 1966-78 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Time Studies, 1970-75 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Time Studies - Homemaking, 1970-75 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Time Study Papers, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Time-Budget, 1964-66 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Time Budget, 19651964-66 1965 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- I.S.S.C. - The Multinational Comparative Time Budget Research Project, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Time Budget, 1966-67 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Time-Budgets and Social Activities, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Time-Budgets and Social Activity, Vol., 1975 (Box 1, Folder 29-30)
- Time-Budget (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Employment and Mobility in Inner Urban Areas - An Interpretive Study, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Transport Studies, 1973-81 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Leisure Time Activities, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Planning the Neighborhood, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- NHK Research, 1966-72 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Papers presented at Schloss Laxenburg, Austria, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1973-77 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Printed Material (Box 2, Folder 4-6)
- "Diary Techniques and the Problems of Urban Life" by lan Cullen and Elizabeth Phelps, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- "Time as a Social Indicator" Final Report Dr. John Helmer, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- "The Structure of Activity Patterns" by la Cullen and Vida Godson, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- "Trip Relationships in Urban Areas" by Helmut Holzapfel (Box 2, Folder 10)
- "L'impieqo del Tempo Libero in Una Provincia Economicamente Sviluppata", 1975 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- "Paths in Space-Time Environments" by Bo Lenntorp, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- "Tidsanvandninq och omgivningsstruktur", 1970 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- "Time Allocation, Innovation and Agraric Chanqe - Outline of a Research Project" by Tommy Carlstein, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- "Technology, Time Use and Reqional Development" by Tommy Carlstein, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- "Reqional or Spatial Sociology?" by Tommy Carlstein, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- "Development as a Packinq Process in Spa and Time" by Tommy Carlstein, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- "The Twenty-Four Hours of the Day", Hungarian Central Statistical Office, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- "Czas Wolny wspotczesnosc iperspektywy" by Edmund Wnuk-Lipinski., 1976 (Box 2, Folder L9)
- "Demoqraphische Determinanten stadtischei Personenverkehrs" by Eckhard Kutter, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- "Loisirs des femmes et temps libre" by France Govaerts, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- "Les vinqt-quatre heures du Belge" by Clav Javeau, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- "lifelong allocation of time" by Mr. J. de Calendar, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- "Wzory Spoleczne Wakacji w Polsce" (2 editions), 1971 (Box 2, Folder 24-25)
- "Activity Patterns in the Black Community Coding Manual", Center for Urban and Regional Studies, University of North Carolina, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- "Reference Manual for National SMSA Activity Surveys", 1966 and 1969, Center for Urban and Regional Studies, Universi 3f North Carolina, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Code book for Activity Data Sets -Washington Metropolitan Area, Center, fen Urban and Regional Studies, University c North Carolina, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Card file sets (Box 2, Folder 29)
- "Across the City Line: A White Community in Transition" by Robert B. Zehner and F. Stuart Chapin Jr. Lexington Books, D. C Heath and Company, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- "Blackways in the Inner City" by F. Stuart Chapin, Jr. Edgar W. Butler and Frederic C. Patten. Center for Urban and Regional Studies, University of North Carolina, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- "Human Time Allocation: A Case Study of Washington, D. C." by Philip G. Hammer, Jr., and F. Stuart Chapin, Jr. Center of Urban and Regional Studies, University of North Carolina, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- "A Probabilistic Model for Residential Growth" by Thomas G. Donnelly, F. Stuart Chapin, Jr. and Shirley F. Weiss. Center for Urban and Regional Studies, Institute for Research in Social Science, University of North Carolina, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- "Moving Behavior and Residential Choice A National Survey" by Edgar W. Butler, F. Stuart Chapin, Jr., George C. Hemmens, Edward J. Kaiser, Michael A Stegman, and Shirley F. Weiss. Center for Urban and Regional Studies, University of North Carolina, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- "A Review of the Social and Physical Concepts of the Neighborhood as a Basis for Planning, Residential Environments" by Alan Richman and F. Stuart Chapin, Jr. Department of City and Regional Planning, University of North Carolina, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- "Hard Living on Clay Street A Study of Blue Collar Families" by Joseph T. Howe with forward by F. Stuart Chapin, Jr. Center for Urban and Regional Studies, University of North Carolina, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- "A Review of the Social and Physical Concepts of the Neighborhood as a Basis for Planning Residential Environments" by Alan Richman and F. Stuart. Chapin, Jr. Department of City and Regional Planning, University of North Carolina, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- "Factors Influencing Land Development Evaluation of Inputs for a Forecast Model" by F. Stuart Chapin, Jr. and Shirley F. Weiss in collaboration with Thomas G. Donnelly. Institute for Research in Social Science, University of North Carolina, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- "Some Input Refinements for a Residential Model" by F. Stuart Chapin, Jr. and Shirley F. Weiss in collaboration with Thomas G Donnelly. Center for Urban and Regional Studies, Institute for Research in social Science University of North Carolina, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- "Household Activity Systems - A Pilot Investigation" by F. Stuart Chapin, Jr. and Henry C. Hightower. Center for Urban and Regional Studies, Institute for Research in Social Science, University of North Carolina, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- "Systems of Urban Activities and Time: An Interpretative Review of the Literature" by John R. Ottensmann with acknowledgment to F. Stuart Chapin, Jr. Center for Urban and Regional Studies, University of North Carolina, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- "The Community Network: An Input-Output Approach" by Elliott A. Krause, Bellenden R. Hutcheson, Margaret Oppenheimer, and Wassily Leontief (Box 3, Folder 13)
- "The 1979 Time Use Study Method" by Liris Niemi (Box 4, Folder 1)
- "Use of Time in Finland" by Liris Niemi, Salme Kiiski, Mirja Liikkanen, 1 9 7 9 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Department of Household Economics and Management, Cornell University - Katherine E. Walker's study, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Research Papers in Geography. University of Newcastle N.S.W., no. 11: Time Experiences and Operational Environments Don Parkes, Nigel Thrift, Eric Woolmington, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Research Papers in Geography, no. 12: Relative Isomorphism of Activity Structures: A Graph Theoretic Approach, Dr. Don Parkes and Dr. Wal Wallis, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Research Papers in Geography, no. 14: On the Significance and Role of Time for Human Geography and Social Science, Dr. Don Parkes, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- TASK 05 - Coding Manual for Combined 1966-1969 Surveys, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Stuart Chapin career background and awards, 1963-2014 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Recommendations on various bills/legislation (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Recommendations on various bills/legislation (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Recommendations on various bills/legislation (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1981-1985 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1981-1985 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1981-1985 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Activity analysis, 1966-1974 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- "The Residential Choice Process," final report, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Residential growth, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Urban planning, 1947-1978 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Columbia River Gorge, National Scenic Area Act, 1984-1993 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Management Plan for the Columbia River Gorge National Scenic Area, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Nomination as Fellow of AICP, by Richard P. Benner, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 14)
- "Remembering some early DCRP benefactors," by Stuart Chapin, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Open letter to U.S. Global Change Research Program regarding climate change, 2015 (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Essay, by Dave Godschalk, on Chapin regarding ACSP award, 2015 (Box 5, Folder 17)
- Columbia River Gorge material, ca. 1980's-2000's (Box 6, Folder 1-12)
- Climate change impacts in the US, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 13)
- Oak Groves series, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 14)
- Memo - land capability classification system, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 15)
- Background notes, Chapin Fund proposal, 2013 (Box 6, Folder 16)
- Articles and papers, 1949-2014 (Box 6, Folder 17)
- Daedalus - v. 96 no. 3, v. 97 no. 4, v. 102 no. 4, 1967-1973 (Box 6, Folder 18)
- On The Strategy of Planning", by Abraham Kaplan, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 19)
- Interview with Michael Oppenheimer, 2014 (Box 6, Folder 20)
- Correspondence, 1984, 1991, 2014 (Box 6, Folder 21)
- Land protection - Washington state handbook, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 22)
- Regional land use, 1991-1992 (Box 6, Folder 23)
- Indian Tribes as Sovereign Governments, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 24)
- Department of City and Regional Planning, 50th Anniversary Celebration Alumni directory, 1996 (Box 6, Folder 25)
- Centre for Research in the Social Sciences, no. 18, 23, 26, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 26)
- National Forest Landscape Management, v. 2, ca. 1970's-2000's (Box 6, Folder 27)
- Career Overview, Undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Stuart Jr. Awards, 1963-1993 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Approaches to Theory Formulation, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- UNC Courses in Planning Theory for PhD Students, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Notes from readings in other fields with possible applications to Planning Theory, Undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Grant proposals, 1957-1974 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  Access restricted to the permission of the curator.
- Household activity studies, 1966-1976 (Box 7, Folder 7)
- System of Urban Activities and Time: And Interpretative Review of the Literature, 1972; Ottensmann, John R. (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Activity classification, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Game analyses, 1972 (Box 8, Folder 2)